Guide to the Wyndham Robertson Papers 1768-1925
University of Chicago Library
Robertson, Wyndham. Papers
1768-1925
6 linear feet (12 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Wyndham Robertson, the 20th governor of Virginia actively corresponded with generals during the civil war. Additionally, he traced his family heritage to Pocahontas and authored historical texts. This collection contains family letters business papers, letters to civil war officials, family records and historical research.
Information on Use
Access
No restrictions
Biographical Note
Wyndham Robertson (1803-1888), the 20th governor of Virginia actively corresponded with southern generals during the civil war. Additionally, he traced his family heritage to Pocahontas and authored historical texts.
Scope Note
The Wyndham Robertson Papers contains approximately 2,300 letters, 1,200 receipts and accounts, and 250 deeds and legal documents. It is housed in twelve manuscript boxes. The material is broken up into four categories, the Robertson family correspondence arranged chronologically, John Robertson Correspondence, the Loyal Company papers arranged chronologically (1 1/2 boxes), and miscellaneous bound material such as account books, the family register, and books and magazines used by Robertson in his historical researches.
The family papers written before 1815 largely consist of the correspondence of Wyndham Robertson's grandfather, Archibald Robertson, a factor on the James River, to his family in Glasgow. Family affairs were the main subject of the correspondence which was continued by Wyndham's father, William. An eighteenth century commonplace book and two diaries of travel dated 1776 and July, 1797, presumably of Wyndham's father, date from this period.
In 1815 the correspondence of Wyndham, himself, commences. His early letters are principally to his father and to three of his brothers, John Robertson, member of the
Virginia legislature, attorney general of the state in 1823 and congressman, 1834; to Thomas Bolling Robertson, governor of Louisiana; and Powhatan Robertson. After his sojourn at William and Mary College from 1819 to 1821, he wrote to many of the friends he made there. From the time of his marriage to Mary F. Trigg Smith in 1831 until the Civil War, which includes the period of his governorship (1836-1838) there is singularly little in the collection dealing with his political career. The letters are addressed to Wyndham and are largely from his family and are concerned with family affairs, although in the years before 1838 Wyndham was immersed in law and politics and after that date was concerned with several business ventures. The correspondence does, however, give numerous descriptions and insights into Southern ante-bellum society. Particularly interesting in this respect are the letters of Wyndham's nephew, Henry Skipwith, and his niece, Gay Bernard, during the latter's stay in the Washington society ruled by the Calhouns. There are also some letters and accounts concerning Wyndham's estate at Abingdon, part of his wife's dowry, his plantation of Bayou Black in Louisiana, and his land speculations in Arkansas. Although there is little of sustained correspondence on political matters, the following individual letters are of interest: the original of the letter of resignation of Governor Tazewell to Wyndham Robertson, March 30, 1836; over a dozen letters written by Nicholas P. Trist to Wyndham between the years 1830 and 1860; a letter from Nicholas Biddle to Wyndham, February 21, 1839.
Beginning with the convention of 1856 and continuing through the year 1870, the correspondence is rich in political matter of the Civil War both for the state of Virginia and, especially in 1860, at the national level. The tribulations of the family during the years of battle and the struggle to retrieve the family's shattered fortunes after the war are fully recorded in their papers and letters. Noteworthy are letters from Edward Bates and General Winfield Scott during the election crisis of 1860 and from Generals Curtis Lee, Robert E. Lee, and J.E.B. Stuart, and from Samuel J. Tilden during the war.
The papers of Wyndham Robertson from the end of the Civil War until his death in 1888, although containing scattered political correspondence, are principally concerned with his business interest in the Buena Vista Plaster Company managed by himself and his two sons, Frank and Wyndham, and his antiquarian studies in the history of Virginia, particularly work on his book, The Descendants of Pocahontas, which was undertaken even before the outbreak of the Civil War. Wyndham Robertson was particularly proud of his descent from Pocahontas (he named one of his children Pocahontas, and another Powhatan). His genealogical papers contain extensive early documentation of the history of the Boiling family.
During the last years of his life, Wyndham had an active correspondence with other famous Virginia historians of his day such as William Wirt Henry, Alexander Brown, Hugh B. Grigsby, Conway Robinson, and Phillip S. Slaughter. The papers from 1888 to 1925, the date of the sale of the Buena Vista Plaster Company, record the growth of the Company and its problems under Wyndham's sons, Frank and Wyndham. Some reminiscences of the younger Robertsons are also contained in this part of the collection.
Because of its unique political interest the correspondence between Wyndham and his elder brother, John, extending from 1818 to 1872 has been treated as a distinct series within the collection. John Robertson sent lengthy reports of the current Washington scene after his election to Congress in 1834.
The papers of the Loyal Company of Virginia, previously dispersed by date through the collection, comprise a third chronological series, bearing no relationship to the rest of the Robertson papers. Captain Francis Smith, Wyndham's father-in-law, was a leading member of the Loyal Company during its last years. Wyndham apparently acquired the papers when he became executor of Smith's estate in 1840. The papers date from the mid-eighteenth century and contain land surveys, receipts, land grants, accounts, and records of court litigations. Notable are a series of fourteen grants of land on parchment dated between 1785 and 1834 signed by the following governors of Virginia: Patrick Henry, Edmund Randolph, Beverly Randolph, Robert Brooke, James Wood, James Monroe, John Page, James Barbour, and Littleton W. Tazewell.
Three groups of papers comprise the fourth series, Miscellaneous Robertson Papers, at the end of the collection: Robertson's Library of Books and Magazines Used in his Historical Researches; Scrapbooks and Diaries; and Robertson's Research Papers on the Descendants of Pocahontas.
Related Resources
The following related resources are located in the Department of Special Collections:
http://www.lib.uchicago.edu/e/spcl/select.html
Subject Headings
Robertson, Wyndham, 1803-1888; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; Pocahontas, d. 1617; Robertson, John, 1787-1873; Stuart, Jeb, 1833-1864; Tilden, Samuel J. (Samuel Jones), 1814-1886; Southern States-History-1775-1865; United States-Politics and government-1861-1865; Virginia-History-1775-1865; Virginia-History-Civil War, 1861-1865; Governors-Virginia; Robertson family
INVENTORY
- Series I: Wyndham Robertson Family Correspondence
  - March 6, 1740-April 1768 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - June 1768-Jan. 28, 1773 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - July 3, 1773-July 15, 1774 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - May 15, 1779-March 1785 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - July 5, 1786-May 11, 1799 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - March 1801-Dec. 17, 1811 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - March 22, 1815-July 20, 1818 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - March 12, 1819-Oct. 18, 1819 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Oct. 27, 1819-Dec. 26, 1819 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Jan. 9, 1820-Feb. 24, 1820 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Feb. 28, 1820-April 30, 1820 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - May 1, 1820-May 27, 1820 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - June 16, 1820-June 30, 1820 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - July 5, 1820-Oct. 11, 1820 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Nov. 1, 1820-Dec. 26, 1820 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Jan. 14, 1821-Feb. 24, 1821 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - March 5, 1821-April 8, 1821 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - April 9, 1821-April 29, 1821 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - May 7, 1821-July 27, 1821 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - July 28, 1821-Oct. 29, 1821 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Nov. 1, 1821-Dec. 29, 1821 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Jan. 30, 1822-March 8, 1822 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - March 30, 1822-July 23, 1822 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Aug. 12, 1822-Dec. 31, 1822 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Jan. 17, 1823-Jan. 8, 1824 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Nov. 9, 1824-Aug. 4, 1825 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Aug. 7, 1825-Sept. 24, 1826 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Feb. 27, 1827-March 10, 1828 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - March 18, 1828-Aug. 10, 1829 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Aug. 11, 1829-Dec. 1829 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Jan. 1, 1830-Aug. 12, 1830 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Aug. 19, 1830-Oct. 23, 1830 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Oct. 25, 1830-Dec. 9, 1830 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Jan. 13, 1831-June 19, 1831 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - June 22, 1831-Aug. 17, 1831 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Aug. 18, 1831-Dec. 18, 1831 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Jan. 20, 1832-June 1832 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - June 2, 1832-Aug. 17, 1832 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Aug. 18, 1832-Dec. 18, 1832 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Jan. 30, 1833-May 6, 1833 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - June 1833-Sept. 16, 1833 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Sept. 25, 1833-Nov. 1833 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Jan. 29, 1834-July 26, 1834 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - July 29, 1834-Nov. 21, 1834 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - n.d. [1835?]-Sept. 4, 1835 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Sept. 11, 1835-Nov. 8, 1835 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Nov. 13, 1835-Dec. 20, 1835 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Jan. 20, 1836-March 30, 1836 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - April 10, 1836-Aug. 3, 1836 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Aug. 20, 1836-Dec. 26, 1836 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Jan. 1, 1837-July 6, 1837 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Aug. 6, 1837-Nov. 2, 1837 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Oct. 24, 1837-Dec. 27, 1837 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Jan. 7, 1838-May 5, 1838 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - May 20, 1838-Aug. 13, 1838 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Aug. 20, 1838-Dec. 22, 1838 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Jan. 6, 1839-April 3, 1839 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Apr. 13, 1839-May 27, 1839 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - June 2, 1839-Dec. 16, 1839 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - n.d. [1840?]-May 30, 1840 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - June 9, 1840-Oct. 9, 1840 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Oct. 21, 1840-Dec. 24, 1841 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Jan. 1, 1842-July 6, 1842 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Aug. 8, 1842-Feb. 3, 1843 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Feb. 8, 1843-Dec. 18, 1843 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Feb. 20, 1844-Mar. 25, 1845 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Mar. 27, 1845-Jan. 5, 1846 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Jan. 9, 1846-Dec. 30, 1846 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Jan. 14, 1847-Sept. 4, 1847 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Oct. 8, 1847-Nov. 24, 1848 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Nov. 25, 1848-Dec. 30, 1849 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - n.d. [185-?]-Sept. 11, 1851 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Sept. 26, 1851-Sept. 4, 1852 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Sept. 11, 1852-Dec. 26, 1853 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - n.d. [1854]-Sept. 24, 1855 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Sept. 25, 1855-July 30, 1856 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Aug. 6, 1856-Dec. 30, 1856 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - n.d. [1857]-June 22, 1857 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - July 5, 1857-Jan. 22, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Jan. 27, 1858-Aug. 7, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Aug. 17, 1858-Dec. 12, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Jan. 5, 1859-Apr. 24, 1859 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Apr. 28, 1859-Aug. 6, 1859 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Aug. 22, 1859-Dec. 21, 1859 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - 1860 [n.d.]-Mar. 25, 1860 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Mar. 27, 1860-June 18, 1860 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - July 16, 1860-Nov. 1, 1860 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Nov. 2, 1860-Dec. 27, 1860 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - 1861 [n.d.]-Apr. 27, 1861 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Apr. 28, 1861-June 30, 1861 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - July 1, 1861-Aug. 3, 1861 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Aug. 21, 1861-Dec. 26, 1861 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - 1862 [n.d.]-July 4, 1862 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - July 5, 1862-Dec. 25, 1862 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Jan. 8, 1863-June 12, 1863 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - June 18, 1863-Oct. 18, 1863 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Oct. 28, 1863-Dec. 28, 1864 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - 1865 [n.d.]-June 26, 1865 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - July 31, 1865-Dec. 31, 1865 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - 1866 [n.d.]-Feb. 12, 1866 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Feb. 14, 1866-May 16, 1866 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - May 18, 1866-Dec. 19, 1866 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - 1867 [n.d.]-May 16, 1867 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - May 20, 1867-Dec. 31, 1867 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - 1868 [nd.]-Apr. 1, 1868 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Apr. 3, 1868-July 12, 1868 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - July 20, 1868-Dec. 30, 1868 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - 1869 [n.d.]-Feb. 16, 1869 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Feb. 17, 1869-Aug. 4, 1869 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Aug. 6, 1869-Dec. 24, 1869 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - 1870 [n.d.]-Apr. 3, 1870 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Apr. 4, 1870-July 14, 1870 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - July 27, 1870-Dec. 31, 1870 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - 1871 [n.d.]-Mar. 1, 1871 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Mar. 12, 1871-June 19, 1871 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - July 1, 1871-Dec. 28, 1871 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - 1872 [n.d.]-Apr. 6, 1872 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Apr. 9, 1872-July 5, 1872 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - July 9, 1872-Dec. 31, 1872 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - 1873 [n.d.]-Feb. 11, 1873 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Feb. 26, 1873-May 18, 1873 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - June 1873-Dec. 27, 1873 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - 1874 [n.d.]-May 23, 1874 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - June 1, 1874-Dec. 19, 1874 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - 1875 [n.d.]-Feb. 4, 1875 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Feb. 9, 1875-Apr. 14, 1875 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Apr. 20, 1875-July 16, 1875 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - July 24, 1875-Dec. 29, 1875 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - 1876 [n.d.]-June 6, 1876 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - June 9, 1876-Nov. 2, 1876 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Nov. 23, 1876-Dec. 26, 1877 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - 1878 [n.d.]-Sept. 13, 1878 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Sept. 23, 1878-Jan. 7, 1879 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Jan. 30, 1879-July 13, 1879 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - July 23, 1879-Dec. 1, 1879 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Jan. 1, 1880-April 22, 1880 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Apr. 24, 1880-July 30, 1880 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Aug. 9, 1880-Dec. 14, 1880 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - 1881 [n.d.]-May 10, 1881 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - May 21, 1881-Dec. 30, 1881 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - 1882 [n.d.]-May 8, 1882 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - May 12, 1882-July 31, 1882 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Aug. 7, 1882-Dec. 30, 1882 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - 1883 [n.d.]-March 28, 1883 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Apr. 1, 1883-Aug. 13, 1883 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Aug. 24, 1883-Dec. 31, 1883 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Jan. 1, 1884-Apr. 26, 1884 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - May 1, 1884-Feb. 11, 1885 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Feb. 13, 1885-Sept. 1, 1885 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Sept. 8, 1885-Dec. 31, 1885 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - 1886 [n.d.]-Mar. 10, 1886 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Mar. 11, 1886-Sept. 11, 1886 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Oct. 1, 1886-Nov. 11, 1886 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Nov. 13, 1886-Dec. 31, 1886 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Jan. 1, 1887-Mar. 28, 1887 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Mar. 30, 1887-July 22, 1887 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - July 23, 1887-Sept. 16, 1887 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Sept. 22, 1887-Dec. 10, 1887 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Jan. 6, 1888-Feb. 14, 1888 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Feb. 15, 1888-Feb. 17, 1888 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Feb. 18, 1888-Dec. 25, 1888 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Feb. 14, 1889-Dec. 3, 1889 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Dec. 23, 1889-Apr. 3, 1890 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Apr. 9, 1890-July 16, 1890 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Sept. 4, 1893-July 1894 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - July 1895-Mar. 6, 1899 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Nov. 6, 1902-Apr. 18, 1904 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Apr. 21, 1904-Feb. 20, 1906 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Feb. 28, 1906-Dec. 23, 1908 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Jan. 4, 1909-Apr. 24, 1909 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - May 1909-Jan. 6, 1912 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Jan. 8, 1912-Oct. 13, 1914 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Mar. 22, 1915-Mar. 30, 1921 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Nov. 12, 1921-Aug. 20, 1923 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Nov. 23, 1923-July 3, 1925 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Undated papers (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous undated papers (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous undated papers and correspondence (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Undated correspondence (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Undated correspondence (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous newspaper clippings (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Undated correspondence (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Undated papers, speeches, etc (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous undated correspondence (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - "Extracts-Fugitive Poetry" (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Undated correspondence (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Undated correspondence (Box 7, Folder 23)
- Series II: John Robertson Correspondence
  - Oct. 13, 1818-Aug. 3, 1825 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Aug. 10, 1825-July 15, 1827 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Aug. 6, 1827-Sept. 9, 1829 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Feb. 21, 1830-Sept. 5, 1833 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Aug. 20, 1834-Jan. 22, 1835 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Jan. 23, 1835-Mar. 31, 1835 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - 1836 [n.d.]-Feb. 18, 1836 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Feb. 29, 1836-May 3, 1836 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - May 4, 1836-June 10, 1836 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - June 13, 1836-Dec. 30, 1836 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Jan. 1837-Mar. 7, 1837 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Aug. 3, 1837-Feb. 25, 1838 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Mar. 2, 1838-Dec. 24, 1838 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Jan. 3, 1839-Aug. 3, 1839 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - July 2, 1843-Nov. 9, 1868 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Nov. 19, 1869-Mar. 15, 1872 (Box 8, Folder 16)
- Series III: Loyal Company Papers
  - July 14, 1752-Jan. 14, 1783 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Jan. 15, 1783-Nov. 1, 1791 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - May 22, 1793-May 30, 1799 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Dec. 20, 1799-Nov. 15, 1800 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Feb. 1801-1802 [n.d.] Includes Loyal Company Account Book for Dec. 31, 1801-Dec. 31, 1820 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Jan. 26, 1802-June 10, 1802 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - June 11, 1802-Jan. 4, 1804 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Apr. 23, 1804-Oct. 13, 1806 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - May 20, 1807-[1809] (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Oct. 21, 1809-May 26, 1811 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - June 17, 1811-Dec. 10, 1812 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Mar. 1813-Dec. 7, 1813 (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Jan. 9, 1814-Mar. 28, 1814 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Apr. 11, 1814-Sept. 19, 1815 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Oct. 30, 1815-Feb. 14, 1816 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Feb. 19, 1816-Nov. 20, 1817 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Feb. 8, 1818-May 20, 1819 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - May 22, 1819-Jan. 1, 1820 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Feb. 25, 1820-Jan. 1821 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Jan. 1, 1821-Dec. 16, 1822 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Jan. 28, 1823-Sept. 3, 1825 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Jan. 23, 1826-June 2, 1827 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Aug. 24, 1827-Dec. 12, 1827 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Apr. 18, 1828-July 1832 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Oct. 11, 1832-Jan. 1, 1835 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Apr. 7, 1835-Sept. 12, 1837 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Dec. 16, 1837-July 16, 1844 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Maps compiled by Francis Smith in 1812 to be used with Marshall's Life of Washington (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Land grants on parchment by governors of Virginia, undated-Jan. 4, 1797 (6 documents) (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Land grants on parchment by governors of Virginia, Aug. 14, 1797-Aug. 3, 1813 (8 documents) (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Day Book "B," Aug. 1, 1807-May 22, 1808 (Box 9, Folder 19)
- Series IV: Miscellaneous Robertson Research Papers
  - A Correspondence Between Generals Early and Mahone In Regard to a Military Memoir of the Latter (printed pamphlet, n.p., n.d., 20 pp.) (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - The Historical Magazine, no. 1, 1860 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - The Historical Magazine, no. 6, 1860 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - The Historical Magazine, no. 9, 1860 (2 copies) (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Littell's Living Age, no. 658, Jan. 3, 1857 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Du Maurier, George, Pictures of English Society ("From 'Punch' "), New York, D. Appleton, 1884 Ossian's Poems, vol. 2 (printed book, n.p., n.d., 252 pp. (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Peabody Education Fund, Proceedings of the Trustees at Their Twenty-Eighth Meeting, New York, 3 October, 1889, Cambridge, University Press, 1889 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Smith, John, Capt., A True Relation of Virginia... With an Introduction and Notes by Charles Deane, Boston, Wiggin and Lunt, 1866 (unbound) (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Virginia Historical Society, Proceedings..., 1855; Jan. 17, 1852; Feb. 24, 1882 (3 printed pamphlets) (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Warrock's Virginia and North Carolina Almanac, 1864 (Box 10, Folder 10)
- Series V: Scrapbooks and Diaries
  - Family Register, June, 1820 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Diaries, Diary, 1763-1782 Diary, 1797 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Business diary, 1849, Business diary, 1851 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Account book of Pelham Blackford (notary public?), Sept. 13, 1887-June 3, 1889 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Commonplace book, ca. 1780 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook of newspaper clippings, 1858-1873 (articles pasted over pages of diary, "Remarks On Board U.S. Sloop of War Natches, William Mervine, Esq., Commander") (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook of newspaper clippings and correspondence, and printed documents and speeches of Wyndham Robertson, 1836-1871 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - The Plantation Record and Account Book No. 2 Suitable for a Force of 80 Hands or Under, fragment of a printed Plantation Record book kept by overseers Jackson R. Nixon and Holden Wright, 1849-1858, 39 pp., numbered [1-12], 1-4, 101-102, 107-14, 127-140 (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Series VI: Robertson's Papers on the Descendants of Pocahontas
  - Scrapbook of drafts for Wyndham Robertson, The Descendants of Pocahontas; called also Matoa (drafts pasted on pages additional of the Plantation Record and Account Book No. 2 described above) (Box 11, Folder 6-9)
  - Pocahontas Memorial Association (promotional and members' pamphlet containing list of officers, membership information, historical and literary texts) Advertisement for Mrs. Herbert Jones, Princess Charlotte of Wales, London, Bernard Quaritch, 1884) Advertisement for Wyndham Robertson, Pocahontas Alias Matoaka And Her Descendants, Richmond, Virginia, J. W. Randolph and English, 1887 Newspaper clipping, "The Real Pocahontas," reproducing 1616 portrait of Pocahontas at age 21 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Rev. Edward D. Neill, Pocahontas and Her Companions, Albany, N.Y., Joel Munsell, 1869 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - "On Neill," notebook of holograph notes on Neill's Pocahontas and Her Companions Wyndham Robertson, "Strictures of Pocahontas and Her Companions: A Chapter from the History of the Virginia Company of London by Rev. E. D. Neill." Autograph Ms, 18 pp Unbound sheets of E. D. Neill, Pocahontas and Her Companions...(to page 8 only) bearing Robertson's drafts and notes for his "Strictures..." (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Two loose leaf scrapbooks of notes for The Descendants of Pocahontas, including- (Box 12, Folder 4-9)
  - 2 scrapbook bindings; folder of notes entitled, "Notes, Data and Gen(ealogical) correspondence about Pocahontas her portrait, etc." (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Wyndham Robertson, Abingdan, Virginia, to..., October..., 1858. Printed form letter soliciting genealogical information sent by Robertson to his relatives. Descendants of Pocahontas; called also Matoa (printed genealogy, 6 pp.) sent with solicitation letter (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Five annotated copies of Descendants of Pocahontas; called also Matoa (printed genealogy, 6 pp.) (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Responses to inquiries by Robertson regarding the Bolling family and related notes (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Responses to inquiries by Robertson regarding the Bolling family and related notes (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Robert Bolling, b. 1738, Bolling family genealogy (two printed sheets, ca. 1760) (Box 12, Folder 9)